Starts in and whatever happens happens. I'll start send out an email
as soon as I get to work unless someone does this before
to the group you know explaining the situation. Let's see. From what
I understand yesterday we were on the first Mishnah ע"ב, 71b, is
that correct? Are you recording on here?
If it's doing it. If it's working.
Right okay. Hold on.
We are on the first Mishnah ע"ב 71b but I don't know
if it's the first Mishnah. Yeah okay. There are two.
So first Mishnah: ברח עד שלא נגמר דינו ואחר
כך הקיף זקן התחתון פטור ואם משנגמר דינו
ברח ואחר כך הקיף זקן
התחתון חייב.
Barach ad shelo nigmar dino ve-achar kach hikif zakan hatachton patur ve-im
mishenigmar
dino barach ve-achar kach hikif zakan hatachton chayav. So it all depends
on when the גמר דין gmar din was. So remember you know
it's only a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u-moreh. It's only lasts
for a couple months, few months. So afterwards he's
you know you don't put him to death for these things. So
if the גמר דין gmar din if they decided he's guilty while
he was still within that that period, that's the end you know
that's the end part and he somehow ran away and escaped and
couldn't put him to death and then he became too old. Then
because the גמר דין gmar din happened while he was חייב chayav
they still put him to death later even when he gets older.
But if all that happened before meaning
they didn't manage to finish the case and then he ran
away then he became old, too old for this then they don't
put him to death.
Even had he been around at that time you know it wouldn't
have been sentenced for that. Okay? It's pretty
simple
enough point. So אמר רבי חנינא amar Rabbi Chanina בן נח. ben
Noach. So we're trying to compare and contrast this to other cases.
So a non-Jew שבירך את השם. shebeirach et Hashem. So he cursed
God, it's always a euphemism. ואחר כך
נתגייר ve-achar kach nitgayer פטור patur
הואיל ונשתנה דינו ונשתנה מיתתו. ho'il venishtaneh dino venishtaneh mitato. I mean
like this threw me off. Like I was reading the, I don't
know what you have in parentheses, it's both ונשתנה מיתתו. venishtaneh mitato.
That that actually is kind of key to understanding this. So basically
might be easier if I write this up.
The
in parentheses is נשתנה nishtaneh and מיתתו. mitato.
So
if
גמר
דין gmar din
if it happened
if it happened while he was basically
while he's still correct
age. I
don't really know what this means. Okay so
now so that that was our statement: if the בן סורר ומורה
ben sorer u-moreh if his גמר דין gmar din happened while he's
the correct age he's killed. So now let's see if this works
with בן נח. ben Noach.
So בן נח ben Noach the statement was this is Rabbi Chanina.
So we went into so he he was like a מקלל mekalel
right? קלל השם kilel Hashem גדף gidaf whatever you want to call
it. And then then he you know
then he became מישראל mi-Yisrael you know a Jew, a יהודי. Yehudi.
So then let's the question so what happens? Right? If you were
to so let's think about this for a minute. So let's say
you were to do whatever it is you know whatever בן סורר
ומורה ben sorer u-moreh does. He's גנב ganav the זולל וסובא zolel
ve-sova he does all these things right? When he's under he's in
the right age he gets killed. Let's say he were to do
that later.
What did we just say? Nothing would happen to him right? So
בן נח ben Noach
if he's מקלל את השם mekalel et Hashem when he's a בן
נח ben Noach what happens to him?
He gets killed right? That's one of the things. That's one of
the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach right? Let's say
he were to do it as a Jew what would happen to
him?
He'd still get killed right?
You
need two witnesses.
Hey I didn't get to that. I just asked what
happened. Right correct?
So so here so this is a little bit different right? Because
if he's too
old
when he does it then does not get
killed.
Right but either way you'd say if he's a יהודי Yehudi what
would happen if he did it? He'd get killed right? If he
curses God. Correct? Right so far like okay.
But the whole court process is very different, right? Court process, so
you know, that's one, so court process for a Jew, I mean,
once he's once he's a Jew, they don't have different court processes,
you know, when you're Jewish. But here, court process is
different
for
Jews and non-Jews. Have
Jews and non-Jews? So sloppy. I really hate handwriting.
J or whatever. Very hard
to
read.
Okay. Anyway,
but what happened here in this case? So remember, he was young
and became old. Here he was not Jewish and became Jewish. So,
you know, can we compare and contrast what happened? So רבי חנינא's
Rabbi Chanina statement is, he's פטור. patur. Why? Because נשתנה דינו ונשתנה
מיתתו. nishtaneh dino ve-nishtaneh mitato.
So דינו dino doesn't necessarily mean like the verdict, you know, it's
basically the process, the court process changes because as David was saying,
and actually רש"י Rashi says, and we can read it,
נשתנה דינו, nishtaneh dino, meaning the court process. That first רש"י Rashi
in the גמרא, Gemara, דאילו מעיקרא נידון באחד ולא דיין אחד ולא
התראה, de-ilu me-ikara nidon be-echad ve-lo dayan echad ve-lo hatra'ah, so it's
different. Because by non-Jews, it only needs one witness, it only needs
one judge, and you don't even need a warning. By Jews, it's
completely different. You need twenty-three for a capital case, you need warning,
you need two witnesses, right? You need all that. So it's very
different. ונשתנה מיתתו. ve-nishtaneh mitato. So I said I was being a
little flip here, right? Because if he's a בן נח ben Noach
curses God he gets killed, if a יהודי yehudi curses God he
gets killed, but how do you get killed? ונשתנה מיתתו, ve-nishtaneh mitato,
that's the second רש"י, Rashi, דכל מיתת בן נח סייף. de-kol mitat
ben Noach sayif. This is going to be a debated point, but
let's go for this now. בן נח ben Noach is סייף, sayif,
but if you're a Jew, what do you get? You get סקילה,
sekilah, right? סקילה. sekilah. You get something else for that.
So I think it's סקילה. sekilah. Okay. So yeah, it right says,
נשתנה מיתתו דכל מיתת בן נח סייף והשתא בא ונידון בסקילה. nishtaneh
mitato de-kol mitat ben Noach sayif ve-atah ba ve-nidon be-sekilah. That's the
second רש"י. Rashi. ולא אתחייב בהאי מיתה הלכך פטור. ve-lo itchayav be-ha
mita hilkach patur. Right?
So
it's different.
So that's why רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says, therefore, בן נח ben
Noach will get off when, if he, you know, converts. Instead of
being killed, in this case, in this
case,
gets off
when he converts. All right? That's what he says. It changes. Right?
So that's his point. לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesa'yei lei, so now,
okay fine, can we prove it from our משנה Mishnah one way
or the other? ברח עד שלא נגמר דינו ואחר
כך הקיף זקן התחתון פטור. barach ad she-lo nigmar dino ve-achar kach
hikshiz kanat-ton patur. That's the first part of our משנה. Mishnah. So
again, you know, if he runs away
before, you know, there was any adjudication one way or the other,
this בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, and then he becomes too
old, he's פטור. patur. מאי טעמא לאו משום דמינא ושני אשתני.
mai ta'ama lav mishum
de-mina u-shani ishtani. So maybe it's the same reason with what we're
just saying, because, you know, things change. לא שאני הכא דאי עבד
השתא לאו בר קטלא הוא. lo shani hacha de-i avad hashta lav
bar katala hu. No, it's different. I mean, you know, what you're
trying to say is, and that's the thing, you can't prove it
because it's a totally different case. Because as we mentioned, let's say
the whole thing happened when he's above thirteen, and you know, in
whatever many months, a couple months, right? Let's say he's fifteen, he
does it.
Right? Let's say, let's say the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh
did whatever he did at the age of fifteen, would anything happen
to him?
No, right? The בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, he גנב ואכל,
ganav ve-achal, but would he be killed? No, he wouldn't be killed.
Only because he's at this age, right? So you can't compare it.
Whereas a בן נח, ben Noach, if he curses God as a
בן נח, ben Noach, he gets killed. If he curses God as
a יהודי, yehudi, he also gets killed, right? So you can't compare
the two cases basically. Right? So comparing it to that part doesn't
have anything to do with the changing, like, you know, like that
way, it's because, you know, it's because it's not even the פרשה.
parshah. תא שמע, ta shema, let's look at the end.
אם משנגמר דינו ברח ואחר כך הקיף זקן התחתון חייב.
im mishe-nigmar dino barach ve-achar
kach hikshiz kanat-ton chayav. So if the judgment is passed while he's
the right age and then, you know, then for whatever reason it
gets delayed in the execution of the judgment because he runs away,
he's still חייב chayav when you find him again.
But but you could compare the two original actions, you know what
I mean, that took place. In other words,
if the Noahide who converted doesn't curse God
again.
But the
difference is in the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh whether it's
גמר דין gmar din or not. In the בן נח Ben Noach
case, we're dealing with a case where he was never judged, right?
It's not that there was a judgment and then he ran away
and converted or or whatever it is, right, the בן נח Ben
Noach case, he just cursed God then he converted. Right, the question
is, okay, well, you know, then someone comes and says, hey, guess
what, you know, you cursed God at some point, do we kill
him or not?
Well, also here,
if the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh
is judged before his age changed, before he runs away, he's still
responsible no matter how old he gets.
Right, if he's judged, but if he isn't, he isn't, right? And
we're trying to prove that, so we're trying to say is that
the
same, that's exactly what we're trying to prove. But I'm saying that
you could make some, they're rejecting it, but I'm saying you could
make a comparison and
say that according to the original actions there is a parallel. Well,
but the problem is, you know, but what we're
trying
to
say is, yes, but like, you know, the whole process is different
potentially and the whole other end of the hypothesis.
No, I'm just saying that there is a parallel, that's why they
bring the example and then they're going to figure out if it
really holds. Right, I'm just saying that this rejection, I'm saying, doesn't
necessarily prove that the original parallel is not correct, that's all I'm
saying. This rejection says if he does it again then he's held
responsible, but if he doesn't do it again then he's off, the
בן נח. Ben Noach.
That's all I'm saying.
Well, if the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh were to do
it again, he wouldn't be חייב. chayav. Right, I understand. But if
he, and but if he does it
again, I'm saying there's future cases but the original case, the parallel
seems to have some validity, that's
all I'm saying.
Okay. There's a difference between the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh
who's the same person, he just aged out of the penalty zone
as opposed to the בן נח Ben Noach whose conversion is
viewed
as he becomes a whole different person. His family goes, you know,
is no longer his family. It's like he gets a whole new
start. So it makes no sense to, you know, burden him with
what he did before.
Right, and that's the answer to what you're saying, right? In other
words, you know, like the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh just
aged,
that's one thing as opposed to the בן נח Ben Noach that
becomes complete, it's completely different, right? He becomes a different person.
Right, those parts I understand, but I was just relating to the
specifics of this
parallel,
you know, according to the original actions, not according to the future
in any way.
Right, but you know, you can't look at it in isolation though,
that's what they're saying. Okay. So, okay, anyway, so we can't prove
it for the first part, then we try to prove it for
the second part of, you know, whether there was a גמר דין
gmar din while he was in the right age for that
and it happens to be, you know, that was the law that
if there was a גמר דין gmar din but, you know, for
some reason as I said that they couldn't carry it out and
then at some point later after he's aged out, he's, you know,
caught, whatever, and then then now he's still, he's still killed.
So before the first part we tried to say that it's a
proof, now we're seeing that it's a challenge because oh, look, you
see, he's, he's still killed, whereas רב הונא's Rav Huna case about
the בן נח, Ben Noach, he's not killed.
So then the גמרא Gemara says גמר דין קאמרת? התם גברא קטילא
הוא. Gmar din kaamart? Hatam gavra katila hu. What kind of question
is that? I mean like, you know, yeah, okay, the גמר דין
gmar din happened and he's liable to death, but in the בן
נח Ben Noach case there was no דין din yet, right? So
you can't, you know, say what happens if there was a גמר
דין gmar din and then, you know, and then something happens as
to his case and say oh, therefore it's a rejection of his
case that he gets off, when no, but there was no גמר
דין gmar din at that point. Alright, so let's see if we
can still figure this out one way or the other. We can't
figure it out from our משנה, mishna, it's not a support, it's
not a refutation, משנה mishna doesn't apply.
Let's try something else. תא שמע בן נח שהכה את חבירו ובא
על אשת חבירו. Ta shema: Ben Noach she-hika et chaveiro u-va al
eshet chaveiro. So, you know, again, our משנה mishna was proving from
ישראל Yisrael to a בן נח, Ben Noach, now let's deal in
the דינים dinim of בן נח. Ben Noach. So בן נח שהכה
את חבירו ובא על אשת חבירו ונתגייר פטור. Ben Noach she-hika et
chaveiro u-va al eshet chaveiro ve-nitgayer, patur. So he did something he
wasn't allowed to do while he was not Jewish. He committed adultery,
he killed
somebody, actually the order's reversed, he killed somebody or he committed adultery
and then he converted, he's פטור. patur.
But if עשה כן בישראל ונתגייר חייב.
asa ken be-Yisrael
ve-nitgayer, chayav. Let's say he committed adultery with a non-Jewish person and
then he became Jewish then he's פטור, patur, but if he committed
this adultery with a Jewish woman
while he was not Jewish and then he converted he does not
get off.
אמאי? נימא הואיל ואישתני אישתני. Amai? Nima ho'il ve-ishtani ishtani.
So why don't we say, okay, things change, right? You know, once
he becomes Jewish, you know, the whole where, you know, things change,
court process becomes different, the potentially
what we'll see, the מיתה mitah might be different, because ישתנה דינו
ומיתתו ואינן והא
דינו השתנה מיתתו לא השתנה.
yishtane dino umitato ve'einan
veha dino ishtani mitato lo ishtani. So no, we need both. In
other words, remember we said that אי ישתנה דינו וישתנה מיתתו? ei
yishtane dino veyishtane mitato? Like you need the whole court process to
be changed as well as the death penalty to be changed. Let's
say you just had one of those things. Let's say you just
have a court process change. We have to obviously admit that the
court process would change because that, you know, but does the מיתה
mitah change? Because you know, we mentioned
that for ברכת השם, Birkat Hashem, if he did it as he
was a not, when he was not Jewish, his מיתה mitah is
סייף, sayif, but if he did it as he was when he
was Jewish, his מיתה mitah סקילה, skilah, that was for ברכת השם,
Birkat Hashem, but does the same thing apply for these other two
cases?
The Rav says no, the court process changed but the מיתה mitah
is not changed. Why? And we'll see that in a moment as
to what the מיתה mitah is. But, you know, remember we have
to have a little review because remember there was a, what is,
this is a מחלוקת, machloket, you might remember that too. What is
the punishment if you commit adultery with a נערה מאורסה? na'arah me'orasah?
Anyone?
סקילה. Skilah. Yeah, by beheading? סקילה. Skilah. And remember that's a מחלוקת
machloket between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and others, you know, do we
say if it's any, is it any worse to commit it with
a, oh, stoning, סקילה skilah stoning, yeah. So is it any worse
to do it with a נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah than with a
married woman? Right, that was that whole מחלוקת, machloket, right? You know,
if you did it with a married woman, according to the חכמים's
Chachamim view,
it's not סקילה skilah and it's, what was it? I'm getting
confused with this, it's, I think is, it should
be סייף, sayif, right? It's סייף. sayif. So that's, you know, so
סייף sayif with a married woman, that's the consensus of adultery,
נערה
מאורסה,
na'arah
me'orasah, סקילה, skilah,
אשת
איש,
eshet ish,
סייף. sayif.
Okay,
so let's say he were to commit this as a Jew with
a married woman, you get סייף. sayif. If
he were to as a בן נח, ben Noach, סייף, sayif, right?
So that's with a married woman. But with a נערה מאורסה, na'arah
me'orasah, it would be different. So it would be ישתנה דינו, yishtane
dino, it would be ישתנה מיתתו. yishtane mitato. But with a married
woman, it would be the same. So the question is, what is
this case talking about, right? When we say with a woman? Okay,
so
alright, anyway, let's read this again. בן נח, Ben Noach,
let me read it again, ששיחק באשת חברו ונתגייר פטור ואחר כך
באשת ישראל ונתגייר חייב. sheshichak be'eshet chaveiro venitgayer patur ve'achar kach be'eshet
Yisrael venitgayer chayav. So as a non-Jewish person and then he converted,
he'd be exempt. But if he did this as a, you know,
he did this as a בן נח, ben Noach,
he does it with a Jewish woman, and then he converted, he'd
still be חייב. chayav. But the question is, but why? Why don't
we just say that things change? So the גמרא Gemara answers, no,
because you
need in order to get out of it, you need both things
to change, you need דינו ומיתתו ואיננה, dino umitato ve'einana, והא דינו
השתנה אבל מיתתו לא השתנה, veha dino nishtana aval mitato lo nishtana,
it hasn't changed because it would, you'd still be put to death
in the same way regardless of whether he converted.
So okay. בשלמא רוצח, Bishlama rotzeach, okay, remember there's two cases, right?
One was killing somebody and the other was adultery. Remember we mentioned
both those cases. If he did either of those, you know, depending
on whether he did it with a Jewish person or not, he
gets off or not. בשלמא רוצח, Bishlama rotzeach, מעיקרא סייף, me'ikara sayif,
if
you as a בן נח, ben Noach, the principle we're saying right
now is that anything he does as a בן נח ben Noach
is סייף. sayif.
Whatever punishment it is, it's always סייף. sayif. Okay, this is a
little complicated, this whole גמרא Gemara today. והשתא סייף. Ve'hashta sayif. Okay.
And then if he did this
now as a Jew, he'd also get סייף. sayif. So okay, so
I can understand that. So therefore, since the מיתה mitah stays the
same, right? You don't say enough changed when he, if he did
this with a Jew. מיתה Mitah didn't change, so therefore if he
did this with a Jew, he'd be חייב, chayav, whereas if he
did it with a not, with a not Jewish woman. But אלא
אשת איש מעיקרא סייף והשתא חנק.
ella eishet
ish mei'ikara saif vehashta chenek.
As a בן נח, ben noach, he did this with a... not...
if he did this again, if he
committed adultery, all of which we were mentioning a second ago is
סייף, saif, but now, if he did it with an אשת איש,
eishet ish, it'd be חנק. chenek.
It's a different punishment anyway. So, he went from סייף saif to
חנק. chenek.
So, okay, so what does that mean? So then therefore we still
have our question,
because okay, I can understand the murder case, right, but here
not only was the court process different, because you know, if you
did all this as a non-Jewish person, the court process is different,
but now the punishment would be different too, right? So the punishment
goes from one to another, it goes from סייף saif to חנק.
chenek. So if both things are changing, why is he חייב chayav
if he does this with a Jewish person and then converts? That
was the statement, that if he did this with a Jewish person
and then he converts, he's חייב. chayav. But why? We just said
that, you know, the court process is different—I know it's very complicated—the
court process is different, and the מיתה mitah would be
different, right? You with me? Sort of? Maybe?
Yeah,
it's as good as it's gonna get.
So the answer
is בנערה המאורסה. benarah hame'orasah.
Right, because this would be an אשת איש, eishet ish, right? You
know we said, again, the statement was בעל אשת חברו. ba'al eishet
chaveiro. So what do we mean by אשת חברו? eishet chaveiro? Right?
Do we mean a fully married woman or do we mean like
a, you know, an engaged kind of woman? We'll see if there's
a problem with that. The answer is no,
בנערה המאורסה, benarah hame'orasah, דאידי ואידי בסקילה. de'idi ve'idi biskilah.
נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah is different, right?
סקילה skilah is the thing.
So therefore, nothing would have changed, right?
Meaning סקילה skilah and סקילה. skilah. So you know, based on what
we said, then that's not enough to get you out of everything,
because you need both things to change in order to be פטור.
patur. If one of these things, in this case the punishment, stayed
the same, then he wouldn't be פטור. patur.
But wait a minute, והא בשישראל דאשת חברו קתני. veha besheyisrael de'eishet
chaveiro katani. So what do you mean with נערה מאורסה? na'arah me'orasah?
Yeah, fine, you could say נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah, you know the
מיתה mitah would be the same, but do non-Jews have a concept
of נערה מאורסה? na'arah me'orasah?
No, right? So for them it's just marriage. No, there's no halachic
נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah with them.
Jews or non-Jews? Non-Jews, right?
So meaning you know, we said that if you did אשת חברו
eishet chaveiro it's one way, if you did it with a ישראלית,
yisraelit, then it's another, right? So what we're trying to say is
that the cases seem to be parallel. Whatever you know, like the
same case in the Jew is, in you know, if it happened
amongst two non-Jews was ruled one way, whereas if it was a
Jew and a non-Jew, right, he'd be ruled differently, right? So I
understand אשת איש. eishet ish. A בן נח ben noach has an
אשת איש eishet ish and we have an אשת איש. eishet ish.
But you can't say that you know, we're comparing what you did
with a non-Jew to a non-Jew with a נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah
to what you did as a non-Jew to a Jew with a
נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah, right, because that's not parallel. Because yes, a
Jew and a non-Jew, that can happen. We can have a Jewish
נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah and then this בן נח, ben noach, you
know, committed adultery with her. But you can't have a non-Jewish person
do adultery with a non-Jewish נערה מאורסה. na'arah me'orasah. They don't have
a law of נערה מאורסה. na'arah me'orasah. So you can't say that's
what the case is. So if you can't say that's what the
case is, then it has to be אשת איש. eishet ish. And
אשת איש, eishet ish, then we have the same question. It goes
from one form of punishment to another, חנק, chenek, right? That's so
we still have the question. If then, so again, the question was
that if the מציאות metziut changed, meaning like the whole court process
changed, and that we know, that we're never debating, right? And also
the punishment changes, then why do we say that if it happened
you know, non-Jew to Jew, then you're חייב? chayav? It should be
פטור patur because again the court process changed and the מיתה mitah
also changed, right?
Murder, murder you know, was another story, murder you know, but this
אשת איש, eishet ish, we have a bigger problem with the אשת
איש eishet ish part.
Okay,
so that was our... so now what do we do? אלא כי
קאמרת בחמורה מיניה שייכא. ella ki kamrat bachamurah mineih shaicha. So sort
of like okay, fine, but like it depends which way you're going,
right? Are you upgrading מיתות mitot or are you downgrading מיתות? mitot?
Right? So sort of like you know, יש בכלל מנה מאתיים יש
בכלל מאתיים מנה, yesh biklal maneh matayim yesh biklal matayim maneh, right?
I say you owe me two hundred, you certainly owe me at
least a hundred, right? Like they had that whole thing in מסכת
בבא קמא. masechet bava kamma. So but you know, so and remember
we have that whole question
of
סקילה, skilah,
שריפה, sreifah,
הרג, hereg, and
חנק. chenek.
And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says שריפה... sreifah...
Okay, these are the order
of
the מיתות mitos *mitot*.
So are you upgrading or are you downgrading מיתות mitos. *mitot*? So
a lighter, I mean literally what it means is קלה בחמורה משתכחה
*kala bechamura mishtachacha*. So a lighter punishment is obviously included in a
heavier punishment. So what do we mean? So what do we say
that בן נח Noach *ben Noach* gets? בן נח *ben Noach* basically
says is הרג hereg *hereg* is the same thing as סייף saif,
*saif*. Just so we know.
Why are you saying obviously?
Wait wait wait.
הרג hereg, *hereg* equals סייף saif,
*saif*, right?
So בן נח *ben Noach*...
if one is קלה *kala*
and one is חמורה
*chamura*...
I know.
So בן נח *ben Noach* is always סייף saif, *saif*. So בן
נח *ben Noach* is always הרג hereg *hereg*, right? And then you
go to חנק chenek, *chenek*.
So if it goes from here to here, that's not a... you
know, then that... that... I mean if you get this then certainly
same to get this is, you know, is at least you would
do, so to speak, right? But you know, but if you go
from here to here it's something else. Anywhere up, right? If you
go up, you know, meaning to be, you know, to...
it's different than going down, right? So
basically, so if we were... if we said that he did it
as a בן נח *ben Noach*,
then he would get סייף saif *saif*. If he did this with
an אשת איש eshet ish *eshet ish*, like we were saying a
second ago, he gets חנק chenek *chenek*. So therefore, it would certainly
be
the same... although it's like slightly different, but you can still say
it's in the rubric of being the same מיתה mitah *mitah* so
to speak, right? So if it's in the rubric of being the
same מיתה mitah *mitah*, then we don't say נשתנית מיתתו *nishtanit mitato*.
Right? Remember in order to get off you need both things to
change. This is not a sufficient degree of change. Since he'd be
downgrading his מיתה mitah, *mitah* by going to a Jew, we don't
say it's enough of a נשתנית מיתתו *nishtanit mitato*. If he'd be
upgrading, if he goes let's say from הרג hereg *hereg* to let's
say סקילה skilah, *sekilah*, right? Then we'd say, "Okay, נשתנה nishtana, דינו
ונשתנה מיתתו *nishtana dino venishtana mitato*," then he'd have to get off.
But since this is at least included in this, right? I mean
at least if you got הרג hereg, *hereg* you certainly can say,
"Okay, to get him to be liable for חנק chenek *chenek*, we'd
say that." So therefore he'd still be killed if he converted, if
he did this with a Jewish person.
And your question was why do we say that?
My question was
the statement was it required change in the judicial procedure and in
the form of execution. Right? But so that is a different form.
Right, so read that into the form and severity of execution.
Okay, that's
basically the way we're interpreting it, I mean I would say. But...
okay, back when we studied this we had a whole discussion if
it's severity or if they mean different things. Like I mean the
person dies, how can the... what does it mean then severity of
execution? More torture, less torture? Like what does it mean in practicality?
So I'm just putting it out there that I have a hard
time with it and we don't have to discuss it.
That's fine. The degree of the...
Okay, so remember, so like in other words, if you will, like
all these one of these if you will, like I don't want
to say included, but you get what I mean, you know. If
you do, if you do, you know...
actually I should do this the other way around. Let's do that.
Right?
But you know, this is like the top guy and you know,
so if you get you know, so this would be, you know,
if you will, I don't want to say included, but you know
what I mean when I say that. Like in severity certainly encompasses
everything that's less than that, right? So we can understand, right, that
you know in this... according to the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim*'s view, you
know, his מיתה mitah *mitah* gets downgraded, right, from בן נח *ben
Noach* this is what happened to בן נח *ben Noach* in our
case we're talking about and then ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael*. So certainly, you
know, the מיתה mitah. *mitah* gets downgraded, you still would be liable.
But what about רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*? רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* has a bit of an opposite order. Right? So
here this would be the בן נח *ben Noach* case
and this would be the ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael* case. Right? Still the
same מיתה mitah *mitah*, right?
But we can't say that the חמורה *chamura* includes the קלה *kala*.
This would be, this... if he gets upgraded, he... you know, he's
now getting upgraded. You're changing the מיתה mitah *mitah* to something worse,
right?
In other words, this would include this, but this would not include
that, right? See what I mean? Like so... תניא tanya כוותיה דרבנן
דאמרינן קלה בחמורה *Tanya
kavatei derabanan de'amrinan kala
bechamura*. This is a very... it's a very tough גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
so you know, something like that. אלא לרבי שמעון דאמר חנק chenek
חמור מאי איכא למימר *Ela le-Rabbi Shimon de'amar chenek chamur mai ika
lemimar*? How do you explain that? So then therefore you would say
נשתנית מיתתו *nishtanit mitato* and therefore he should get off, right? That's...
that's basically where we're getting to.
Because because you know because you can't... going from here is different.
You can't make it worse. You can only make it... yeah, I
don't
think it would be the other way around. Right, if you will,
this is like a better מיתה mitah according to the חכמים, Chachamim
right? So that therefore a better מיתה can, you know, therefore to
get an easier מיתה you can certainly say. So therefore, you know,
you'd be still liable. But to get a worse מיתה, that's a
big חידוש. chiddush. So why why would he still be liable to
מיתה if he converted? That was a question. רבי שמעון סבר כדתניא
דבי מנשיא דאמר כל מיתה אמורה בבני נח אינה אלא חנק, Rebbe
Shimon savor katanya d'bei Binashia d'amar kol mitah amura b'Vnei Noach einah
ela chenek, right? So he just disagrees with the assumption. Before we
say, it's all, it works, you know, it was all a question
because they say סייף, saif, right? But if you just say it
was חנק, chenek then this is the same, right? According to רבי
שמעון. Rebbe Shimon, בני נח Bnei Noach and ישראל, Yisrael right?
That's the, that's the answer. It's still on the same plane, he's
still on the same plane, you don't have נשתנה מיתתו. nishtana mitaso.
Therefore he's killed.
Okay. בשלמא
אשת איש מעיקרא חנק והשתא
חנק, Bishlama
eshet ish meikara chenek v'hashta
chenek,
okay fine I understand that. Remember the two questions. There was a
there was a case if he either committed adultery or if he
committed murder, right? We just talked about the whole אשת איש eshet
ish part and then we we tried to bring a proof from
one way or the other, we tried to say, okay, you know,
we understand according to חכמים Chachamim why you're killed because, you know,
it's the change in מיתות mitot isn't sufficient enough, isn't this drastic
enough. Then we had a potential question on רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon
it would be a very drastic change in מיתות. mitot, And we
said no, well, not really, because he thinks that all בני נח's
Bnei Noach מיתות mitot, are חנק chenek. and in this case אשת
איש eshet ish would still be חנק chenek. as a ישראל, Yisrael
therefore he gets killed, right? So I understand that, we how we
answered up this whole אשת איש eshet ish part. But אלא רוצח
מעיקרא חנק והשתא סייף. ela rotze'ach meikara chenek v'hashta saif.
But he goes from a חנק chenek to סייף, saif. right? So
if he goes from a חנק chenek to a סייף, saif then
then that's an upgrade in the in the מיתות, mitot right? That'd
be, if you will, like an also worse מיתה. So why would
he, you know, then you should say that what we were saying
before, that נשתנה, you know, that נשתנה מיתתו נשתנה דינו, nishtana mitaso
nishtana dino, that whole thing. מעיקרא חנק והשתא סייף Meikara chenek v'hashta
saif because, sorry, מעיקרא, meikara, the other one went מעיקרא חנק והשתא
סייף, meikara chenek v'hashta saif, right, that I just flipped it the
wrong way. מעיקרא חנק והשתא סייף, meikara chenek v'hashta saif,
so then the answer is this this whole thing. This is according
to רבי, Rebbe, I was pointing to the wrong side. It'd be
it'd be a question, it's not a question according to the חכמים
Chachamim because they always say הרג hereg. and הרג, right? Because that
was a חכמים's Chachamim view, that בני נח Bnei Noach is always
liable to הרג and, you
know, then as ישראל Yisrael, this would be be, you know, הרג
too. So that wouldn't be a question. According to רבי שמעון, Rebbe
Shimon you know, but you're changing מיתות, mitot because רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon is the one that said that בני נח Bnei Noach is
always is always חנק. chenek, Right, so that's the question, you know,
what's a בני נח Bnei Noach הרג, you know, this is the
חכמים's Chachamim view that חכמים Chachamim
בני
נח
Bnei
Noach is סייף saif
and then רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says that it is חנק.
chenek But what about
the, wait, wait, wait, I gotta I gotta finish this this thought.
I need it for myself.
So so we again, we answered the whole אשת איש eishet ish
part, you know, I don't want to go through that again, but
by murder we say בשלמא אשת איש מעיקרא חנק והשתא חנק bishlama
eshet ish meikara chenek v'hashta chenek אלא רוצח מעיקרא חנק והשתא סייף.
ela rotze'ach meikara chenek v'hashta saif. So חנק chenek or סייף, saif.
or I'm just going to just do this part,
חנק henek. and סייף. saif. So now again this wouldn't this
isn't a question according to חכמים Chachamim, because they don't say they
don't say what we just said, מעיקרא חנק והשתא סייף. meikara chenek
v'hashta saif. They say it'd be סייף saif as a בני נח
Bnei Noach and it'd be סייף sayif now, murder. So that's why
it wasn't a question on the on the חכמים, right? As a
בני נח Bnei Noach he'd be liable to סייף. As a ישראל
he'd be liable to סייף. Therefore he's still liable. We don't say
נשתנה מיתתו. nishtana mitaso. You only need both to get off. But
according to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, it's different. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
says you get חנק, henek. right? מעיקרא חנק meikara chenek and now
it's סייף for murder. That's the punishment for murder. So now you
have נשתנה מיתתו, nishtana mitaso, right? So then the whole question is,
you know, why doesn't he get off? The answer is what we
said before, קל וחומר מעיקרא שיכול, kal v'chomer me'ikara sheyachol, right? Because
רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon views this down down
here,
he views it this way. So חנק henek he would get חנק
henek. as a בני נח, Bnei Noach, right?
According to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon בני נח. Bnei Noach.
And
now he'd get he'd get הרג. But we said already this is
a this is this is easier. So this is easier. This is
this is a better punishment. So if he's getting a better punishment
as a ישראל, you still kill him. It's not enough for נשתנה
מיתתו. nishtana mitaso. It has to be going the other way. He
has to be upgrading his מיתות in order for it to be
נשתנה מיתתו. nishtana mitaso. Downgrading your מיתה is not enough to say
נשתנה מיתתו. nishtana mitaso.
Sort of good there?
Yes.
Okay. So my question is... Okay, so my question is, according to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says that a נח always gets חנק.
chenek Yes. So, but what does he,
what does he do about the Noachide who commits adultery with the
betrothed נערה? na'arah?
But we said that wasn't the question because there's no such thing.
We that can't be our case. Oh because
because they don't have נערה. na'arah. We said that it's, we said
that it has to be parallel cases, we're not talking about that.
Meaning if he committed adultery with a if a Jewish נערה המאורסה,
na'arah hame'orasah,
but that's the only one there would be, right?
Right, no I know, but yeah, so like but we're stuck with
that question.
Is there an exception where he'd be subject to?
Right, let's say let's say this would have but being our statement
wasn't covering that. But so if he committed
adultery, he'd probably be still killed because well no רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon had a whole different view as to what happens if it's
a נערה המאורסה na'arah hame'orasah anyway, right? Didn't he?
Well that's what I'm asking.
So but I mean assuming assuming that
he'd be,
yes he'd still be killed. He'd still be killed if it was
a נערה המאורסה na'arah hame'orasah but we were saying that we're not
but we're not dealing with that case.
Oh I'm just saying because here רבי שמעון saying that a Noachide
always gets strangulation and I'm just curious about that case which says,
right right, but but
he had a different view of what happens with נערה המאורסה. na'arah
hame'orasah. Would he be stoned? Would he agree that the נערה na'arah
gets, that the
Noachide gets stoning for that particular case or not or he always
gets strangulation according to this statement that
that's
all he can get.
Let me think about that.
Well I mean again like I want to review what רבי שמעון
really says about נערה המאורסה na'arah hame'orasah man, he had a different
view of that. But me or maybe he just decided it was
the same thing. I think his view was that אשת איש was
also סקילה, skilah. right? For the נערה המאורסה, na'arah hame'orasah, I think
he didn't, I think he was for certainly נערה המאורסה na'arah hame'orasah
was there. No but you know I don't know because I remember
about the בת כהן, bat kohen, I don't know I don't remember.
Anyway, למה לי למכתב הכא ואחר כך בבגרות תידון בחנק. lema li
lemicatav hacha v'achar kach bebagrut tidon b'henek. So okay
now
yeah so fine. Basically what do we what do we have so
far? We tried you know we had a בן סורר ומורה ben
sorer u'moreh you know who said whatever it said you know in
our in our wall that ברח barakh you know depends when the
גמר דין g'mar din happened. If he was in a פרשה parshah
when the גמר דין g'mar din happened that he still gets killed
if not then not. And then and then we tried to compare
that to רבי חנינא's Rabbi Chanina case about the Noachide, right you
know he curses and then he converts. What happens with that? And
then we tried to prove it from a משנה Mishnah we couldn't,
tried to prove it from other cases, tried to refute it, whatever.
We could we at the end of the day we managed to
deflect all the challenges right? We kept on saying you know that
one way or the other we you know we couldn't say that
his statement was wrong for whatever reason you know either the same
מיתות or like you know a קלה וחמורה kalla v'chamura issue so
you know it wasn't enough of a change to you know to
get him off. So
now let's see if we can actually support what he says. למה
לי למכתב הכא בבגרות תידון בחנק. lema li lemicatav hacha bebagrut tidon
b'henek. So this is a נערה המאורסה na'arah me'orasah
and she
committed adultery and then she became a בוגרת bogeret which is sort
of like you know if you will like our almost like our
parallel case to the בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u'moreh, right? He
committed a sin while he was a certain age and then he
you know aged out of it. So this is נערה המאורסה na'arah
me'orasah committed adultery and then she aged out of it right?
So
תידון בחנק. tidon b'henek. So because what would happen if again because
you know the difference is she committed you know adultery is שייך
shayach with whether you're married or whether you're נערה, na'arah, right? So
it's not exactly parallel to our משנה. Mishnah. But what about the
is it parallel to רבי חנינא's? Rabbi Chanina רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
says that it was a Noachide and you know a Noachide if
he curses Hashem as a Noachide he's killed. If he curses Hashem
as a Jew he's still killed. נערה המאורסה na'arah me'orasah so what
but question you know so but then you know we say again
if ישתנה ממיתתו ishtaneh mimitato whatever that whole thing. But you have
a you have the difference over there with in the as a
Noachide is a different court process right? But a נערה המאורסה na'arah
me'orasah he still the same court process he just has a change
in age. So we're just I mean so it's really not a
good comparison but the גמרא gemara is trying to compare. So if
she was a if she was a נערה na'arah the punishment would
be סקילה. skilah? And then if she's an adult she's you know
it would be חנק. chenek, So what do you do? She aged
out right? So he says okay
so so
you still get
דהיא. d'hi. The ברייתא braita so the ברייתא braita says that she's
still punished with חנק that would be an age you know which
would be just regular adultery case as a woman who reached majority.
בסקילה מאי טעמא לא? b'skilah mai ta'ama lo? So why not סקילה?
skilah לאו משום דהוא השתנה השתנה? lav mishum d'u ishtaneh ishtaneh? Don't
we say oh okay because she changed right? וכל שכן הכא דהשתנה
לגמרי. v'chol sheken hacha d'ishtaneh legamre.
So in the נערה המאורסה na'arah me'orasah you know she's still she's
still Jewish right? Just that the punishment changed because you know if
you do it as a נערה na'arah סקילה sekilah if you do
it as a בוגרת bogeret or older then then it's חנק. So
we say תידון בחנק. tidon b'henek. And then so certainly in this
case this case being the
what we start. with the בן נח שבירך את השם ואחר כך
נתגייר פטור, ben Noach she-beirach et ha-Shem ve-ach kach nitgayer patur, right?
So if we say that, so we would say that everything
changed completely. So to me we're trying to prove that like okay,
she gets the lower in the נערה na'arah stuff, she gets the
lower form, right, of חנק as opposed to סקילה sekilah. because something
changed. That's what we're basically saying. So certainly then we're saying קל
וחומר, kal v'chomer, the רב חנינא Rav Chanina case where everything changed,
the corpus changed and the type of מיתה changed, she would get
off completely. That's what we're trying to say. That's the proof. Now
אמר ליה רבי יוחנן התנא amar leh Rabbi Yochanan hatanna תהא נידונית
בסקילה. tehei nidonit b'sekilah. Okay, that would be true if your assertion
was correct. Meaning the ברייתא beraita asserted that
if she was a נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah and then she became
a
בוגרת, bogeret, what's her punishment? We say okay, then in רב חנינא's
Rav Chanina case when he was a non-Jew, when he was not
Jewish and then he did all this and then everything changed, the
מיתה and the corpus changed and he'd get off, right? So the
answer is so that would potentially be a proof. They're saying no,
but
it's not a proof because truthfully
the emendation according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is that that's not
true, that if she committed adultery as a נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah
and then became a בוגרת, bogeret, she'd get חנק, she would still
get
סקילה. sekilah, So she still gets סקילה, that can't be a proof
that in רב חנינא's Rav Chanina case that he would get nothing,
right? Maybe he should still get something, right? Maybe he should go
from סייף
to whatever, I don't know.
But yeah, it seems like the thing that's sort of floating around
in the background is
when you're deciding the punishment, is the relevant fact your age and
circumstances at the time you did the act or at the time
of judgment? And they're sort of playing with that by talking about
things changed. But really that's what the question is.
Well, I think he ended up saying though is that they need
both to change, you need the corpus and the
ultimate...
but it's a funny concept of change, right? The real question becomes
I
think it's sort of like to put it into modern,
a 12-year-old
kills somebody and by the time he gets around to trial, he's
now aged into being an adult.
Do you punish him as a child because he was a child
when he did it, or do you punish him as an adult
because that's what happened by the time he gets to court?
Right. I mean, but we were saying that it depends when the
גמר דין gmar din happened, right, as opposed to when the...
yeah, which is
that's what he ended up saying though.
Would they punish as an adult in that case?
I don't know.
I mean in our...
No, I'm saying that just raises the question.
No, they wouldn't, would they? I mean, he was... juvenile...
I have no idea about criminal law or stuff like that.
It wouldn't make sense not to, right?
That he should be tried as a juvenile, right? Yeah. I mean,
I think today if it's a really awful crime they try him
as an adult even if he's 12,
but
right.
Okay, anyway, all right, now this next part will get easier, then
it'll get more complicated, but most of the part we're not going
to get to today. So בן עזאי אומר הני דן חמש עשרה
פה, ימות זכאי ואל ימות חייב.
Ben Azzai omer hanei dan chamesh esreh
poh, yamut zakai v'al yamut chayav. So again, it's not so much
because he stole and drank so much that we would really make
him liable to death, but it's what we think is going to
happen where this destructive path will lead you. ימות זכאי ואל ימות
חייב. Yamut zakai v'al yamut chayav. Let him die relatively innocent as
opposed to ימות חייב, yamut chayav, dying later, we'll get to what
we mean by that. ימות חייב. yamut chayav. Then the משנה mishnah
goes on: מיתתן של רשעים הנאה להם והנאה לעולם. mitatan shel rasha'im
hana'ah lahem v'hana'ah l'olam. If רשעים rasha'im get killed, that's a good
thing, good for them, it's good for the world. Why is it
good for them? Because they won't do anything worse, their sinning will
stop, they won't make themselves even worse and it's good for the
world because it prevents more sin in the world, other people will
suffer. But of course the contrast would be for צדיקים tzaddikim that...
לצדיקים רע להם ורע לעולם. l'tzaddikim ra lahem v'ra l'olam. That's a
bad thing. יין ושינה לרשעים הנאה להם והנאה לעולם. yayin v'sheinah l'rasha'im
hana'ah lahem v'hana'ah l'olam. If they're drinking and if they're sleeping, it's
good because I guess at least while they're drinking, mean not after
they get drunk, but while they're drinking at least out of trouble
for a few moments. And then if they're asleep they're not doing
anything bad, that's good. But לצדיקים רע להם ורע לעולם. l'tzaddikim ra
lahem v'ra l'olam. But the צדיקים tzaddikim are sleeping, that's bad because
they're not doing מצוות mitzvot so it's not helping them or the
world. פיזור לרשעים הנאה להם והנאה לעולם. pizur l'rasha'im hana'ah lahem v'hana'ah
l'olam. If they're scattered, if רשעים rasha'im are scattered, that's good because
they can't make a קהל kahal to do bad things so it
limits the amount of evil. But לצדיקים רע להם ורע לעולם. l'tzaddikim
ra lahem v'ra l'olam. צדיקים, tzaddikim, they will not have that supportive
community so that's a bad thing. כינוס לרשעים רע להם ורע לעולם.
kinus l'rasha'im ra lahem v'ra l'olam. The contrast, flip side, if רשעים
rasha'im are gathered together, that's bad because they can hatch all these
bad plans. וצדיקים נאה להם ונאה לעולם, vetzadikim naeh lahem venaeh laolam,
but for
צדיקים. tzadikim.
So תניא רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili basically it’s going to
be the same thing. It’s just going to expand it a little
bit. וכי מפני שאכל זה תרטימר בשר ושתה חצי לוג יין האיטלקי
מביאתו התורה לבית דין וייסקל? vechi mipnei sheachal zeh tartimar basar veshahta
chatzi log yayin haitalki meviato hatorah leveit din veyisakel? Just what because
he just ate a little, he’s minimizing it, it’s because he ate
a little bit of meat and drank a little bit of wine
he’s going to be killed? אלא הגיעה התורה לסוף דעתו של בן
סורר ומורה. ela higiah hatorah lesof daato shel ben sorer umoreh. The
תורה torah knows what’s going to happen in the end. סוף מגמר
נכסי אביו ומבקש לימודו ואינו מוצא ויוצא לפרשת דרכים ומלסטם את הבריות.
sof megamer nichsei aviv umivakesh limudo veino motzei veyotzei leparashat derachim umelistem
et habriyot.
So he’s going to continue along this path, he’s going to deplete
all his parents’ money, and then he’s going to,
in an effort to continue this habit, he’s going to start robbing
other people, and he’s going to kill them if need be. So
אמרה תורה ימות זכאי ואל ימות חייב. amrah torah yamut zakai veal
yamut chayav. Let him be killed now before he’s done anything too
bad, and not when he’s older and really done something a lot
worse. Preemptive punishment?
Does the תורה torah have any other case of
that? Does the תורה torah
have any framework
for putting someone in prison? No.
I mean,
there’s court cases of flogging, but there’s no prison.
No. In other words, there’s no idea of put him in prison
until he matures or rehabilitate him.
Well the only thing we have rehabilitating maybe עבד עברי, eved ivri,
right? He steals, we say that he’s supposed to work and pay
off his debt for the person and that may involve also rehabilitative
process.
But here you don’t. It is strange. And then it goes on,
מיתתן של
רשעים הנאה להם והנאה לעולם. mitatan shel reshaim hanaah lahem vehanaah laolam.
We kill them off now while he’s relatively okay. מיתתן של רשעים
הנאה להם והנאה לעולם mitatan shel reshaim hanaah lahem vehanaah laolam good
things, ולצדיקים רע להם ורע לעולם velatzadikim ra lahem vera laolam bad
things before. שינה ויין לרשעים הנאה להם והנאה לעולם,
sheinah veyayin lereshaim hanaah
lahem vehanaah laolam, sleep and wine for רשעים reshaim is good because
gets them apart a little bit. ולצדיקים רע להם ורע לעולם velatzadikim
ra lahem vera laolam for צדיקים tzadikim it’s bad. שקט לרשעים רע
להם ורע לעולם sheket lereshaim ra lahem vera laolam tranquility for רשעים
reshaim is bad
for all parties concerned and ולצדיקים נאה להם ונאה לעולם velatzadikim naeh
lahem venaeh laolam good for צדיקים. tzadikim. פיזור לרשעים הנאה להם והנאה
לעולם pizur lereshaim hanaah lahem vehanaah laolam scattered for רשעים reshaim is
scattered that's good.
ולצדיקים רע להם ורע לעולם.
velatzadikim ra lahem
vera laolam.
That’s about the Temple,
I mean the dispersion of the wicked in terms of the
Tower of Babel, right?
הבא במחתרת נידון על שם סופו. haba bamachteret nidon al shem sofo.
So okay we have another case of נידון על שם סופו nidon
al shem sofo maybe.
I mean נידון nidon is something taken somewhat loosely. But let's say
you're the person tunneling, you're the thief, you're tunneling under the house,
you want to steal something, then the תורה torah says אם במחתרת
ימצא הגנב והוכה ומת אין לו דמים. im bamachteret yimatzei haganav vehukah
vamet ein lo damim.
So if this גנב ganav is tunneling and the בעל הבית, baal
habayit, the owner sees this guy and then kills him, he’s not
liable for death.
But אם זרחה השמש עליו. im zarchah hashemesh alav. We'll have to
explain that. I mean it's not meant to be taken literally, but
literally I’m going to say then we'll see what it really means.
If the sun shines on him and you kill him, דמים לו
שלם ישלם. damim lo shalem yeshalem. He’d have to pay. אם אין
לו ונמכר בגניבתו. im ein lo venimkar bignevato. And if he doesn't
have enough he’d have to be sold for his to make restitution.
So what is all that about? הבא במחתרת נידון על שם סופו.
haba bamachteret nidon al shem sofo. So let's look at the first
part. אם במחתרת ימצא הגנב והוכה ומת אין לו דמים. im bamachteret
yimatzei haganav vehukah vamet ein lo damim. If the thief is found
tunneling and the בעל הבית, baal habayit, the owner kills him, that's
fine. So basically meaning this guy didn't kill anyone yet, this case,
but
נידון על שם סופו. nidon al shem sofo. We're going to explain
that.
Because we figure he is going to kill, so therefore you have
the right to kill him first, because otherwise you would be killed.
הבא במחתרת ששיבר את החבית. haba bamachteret sheshibar et hachavit. And let's
say we have this case,
he didn't get around to stealing but he broke something along the
way. הבא במחתרת ששיבר את החבית, יש לו דמים חייב, אין לו
דמים פטור. haba bamachteret sheshibar et hachavit, yesh lo damim chayav, ein
lo damim patur. So do we say that this guy has to
pay for what he broke? He’s this thief. So you may have
had the right to kill him. So but we know that, do
we kill him and also make him pay? Right? So we have
the principle of... remember this principle קים ליה בדרבה מיניה? kam leih
bidrabah mineih?
You only get the worse punishment. So like let's say you steal
at the same time of violating שבת, shabbat, you don't have to
pay for what you stole because you get killed for breaking שבת.
shabbat. So in this case what we mean by יש לו דמים
yesh lo damim versus אין לו דמים, ein lo damim, יש לו
דמים yesh lo damim means if you would be liable for killing
this person, this מחתרת. machteret. That's the יש לו דמים. yesh lo
damim. אין לו דמים ein lo damim means you would not be
liable for killing this person.
So there'd be times you might be liable for killing this person
and there'd be times you might
you're not allowed to kill him in all cases basically is what
we're saying, right? And that's the ending אם זרחה עליו השמש. im
zarchah alav hashemesh. The גמרא Gemara will explain or other cases. But
anyway, so if you would be liable for killing him, then...
Therefore
it's not a case that you know it's not a case he
wouldn't be killed right this מחתרת. machtaret. Why would he not be
killed again? Because like you know think of it this way like
the גמרא Gemara it's probably easier to explain the way the גמרא
Gemara will. Like let's say a father and a son right? The
father's tunneling under his son's you know house. Then you know we
know what the father's at least the חזקה chazaka is that the
father will not you know kill the son. We know that. And
the son will know that also that the father will not kill
him. Therefore he doesn't have a right to kill the father because
you know he should just you know somehow incapacitate him but not
kill him right? Whatever let him steal and you know bring him
to judgment. Not like oh my god I gotta kill this guy
otherwise he's gonna kill me. So therefore if let's say the father
broke something since he was never you know subject he would never
even have been subject to death right you know meaning the guy
his son had no right to kill him. Therefore if he breaks
something he has to pay for it right? Because there's no קים
ליה בדרבה מיניה. kim lei b'derabba minei. He's not going to be
killed right?
But but if it's somebody else right and then he breaks something
then that he even if like you know he didn't actually even
you know he didn't get killed like he managed to escape it
out he managed to escape but potentially you know since he would
have been subject to death right this
guy then he doesn't have to pay for something he broke potentially
right? Something he broke. Now let's say you know the גמרא Gemara.
is going to deal with this this part's going to be complicated
let's say it's like okay let's say he didn't break let's say
he has it right? Yeah you know he tunneled under the house
and stole the the china right? And then he got caught right?
Does he have to pay it back?
No. Says no.
Let me just read this little teeny-tiny bit. אמר רבא מאי טעמא
דמחתרת? Amar Rava mai taama d'machtaret? What is this whole why do
why are you allowed to kill this guy who is tunneling under
the you know the house or whatever? חזקה אין אדם מעמיד עצמו
על ממונו.
Chazaka ein adam maamid atzmo
al mamono. So what we know that people aren't going to stand
idly by while all their money is being stolen. והאי מימר אמר:
Ve'hai memar amar: so what's the thought process over here that's going
on? So this hide this this thief is saying in his mind
אי אזילנא קאי אפי ולא שביק לי. ei azilna, kayei appai lo
shavik li. So let's say I go and break into this
house the guy who you know whose house it is he's going
to confront me he's not going to just let me steal his
stuff. וכי קאי אפי קטילנא ליה. Ve'chi kayei appai katilna lei. And
let's say he does that so he's going to confront
me I'm just going to kill him. I'm not you know? But
so therefore to our mind בא להורגך השכם להורגו. ba le'horgecha hashkem
le'horgo.
So knowing that this is the mindset of this this thief who
has now been transformed into a potential murderer the תורה Torah says
alright let's
don't you know we don't need you to stand by and get
yourself killed so rather you can kill this guy. And that's why
the תורה Torah says אם במחתרת ימצא הגנב והכה ומת אין לו
דמים. im b'machtaret yimatzei haganav vehukah vameit ein lo damim.
If this you know guy was found in the in the act
and you killed him you're not liable.
Okay I'm going to stop here because it's already 8:39 and I
forgot. But basically what we're going to deal with is that case
that I mentioned. Like what happens if if it didn't break? Right?
The משנה Mishna deals with the case that whatever it is you
were trying to steal broke. Let's say it's still around
will you have to return it?
So there's a מחלוקת machlokes about that right? קם
ליה בדרבה
מיניה?
Kam
lei b'derabba
minei?
Sorry this is very complicated so you know we didn't get too
far but I'll try to do the rest.
Right there's a מחלוקת machlokes right? קם ליה בדרבה מיניה? Kam lei
b'derabba minei?
I'm sorry אביי
ורבא
Abaye
ve'Rava it's complicated.
Yes about your question right whether he has to return it. So
you're you're stopping at אמר רב amar Rav right? Is that where
we stop?
I'm stopping at אמר רב amar Rav yeah a
few lines into the גמרא.
I just knew this would take a while. I mean I prepared
more but I didn't think I would get too far.
I just feel I didn't get to exactly where I got to
right now.